A Guide to the Virginia Crockford Papers, 1958-1980
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Virginia Crockford Papers, 1958-1980
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 283
3.9 Linear Feet
Virginia Crockford
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The initial deposit was given to the SCA by Mrs. Crockford in November 1990. A second deposit from Mrs. Crockford was made in July 1995.
Biographical/Historical Information
Virginia Allen Crockford (1917-2001) served as head of the City of Richmond's School Board during the late 1960s and early 1970s when integration and busing were fiercely debated topics in the city. Her support in favor of keeping Richmond's schools open through the use of busing to integrate was met with extreme controversy in the city. In their obituary of Crockford, published March 26, 2001, the Richmond Times- Dispatch wrote:
"Despite death threats, public rallies denouncing her personally and one attempt by the Richmond City Council to remove her from office, Mrs. Crockford looked beyond the issues of the day, calling public schools 'our answer'.
Born in Blacksburg, Virginia in 1917, Crockford and her husband, W. Hamilton Crockford III, who became a Richmond Times-Dispatch reporter, moved to Richmond in 1947. She was appointed to the Richmond School Board in 1962, becoming the board's only woman and only the second woman in its history. After a 1970 attempt by City Councilman Howard H. Carwile to remove her from her post as School Board chair was defeated by a 7-1 vote, Councilman James G. Carpenter said of Mrs. Crockford: "She is a person who fights for what she believes is right and who is prepared to take the consequences." [See Times-Dispatch obituary]. She left the board after her term limit expired in 1972. She died March 24, 2001.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists primarily of correspondence and reports concerning Mrs. Crockford's activities as chair of the Richmond School Board. There is a great deal of information on the desegregation of Richmond schools, busing for integration, consolidation of Richmond, Henrico and Chesterfield school districts, and sex education in the public schools. The bulk of the materials cover the years 1969 through 1972.
Arrangement
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in several series and alphabetically by subject therein. Clippings have been removed and those for which Cabell Library does not have microfilm have been duplicated and placed in Series VI. An index to the clippings is attached. One photograph has been removed to the University Photograph Collection.
Organization
Series I--Personal Information (undated)
Series II--Desegregation (undated, 1961-1975)
Series III--Committees (undated, 1955-1972)
Series IV--Richmond School Board (undated, 1958-1980)
Series V--Richmond School Board Minutes (1961-1972)
Series VI--Publications and Clippings (undated, 1948-1982)
Contents List
- Personal Information, undated
  - Personal Information, undated (Box-folder 1.1)
- Desegregation, undated 1961-1975
  - Annexation, undated 1969-1976 (Box-folder 1.2)
  - Bradley v. Board Defendant's Exhibit #1, undated 1970 (Box-folder 1.3)
  - Bradley v. Board Legal Files I, undated 1969-1972 (Box-folder 1.4)
  - Bradley v. Board Legal Files II, undated (Box-folder 1.5)
  - Busing, undated 1970-1972 (Box-folder 1.6)
  - Consolidation, undated 1961-1972 (Box-folder 1.7)
  - Desegregation, undated 1966-1971 (Box-folder 1.8)
  - McDorman, Jane E., undated (Box-folder 1.9)
  - Opening of Schools 1971-1972 (Box-folder 1.10)
  - Parent Advisory Committee on Busing 1975 (Box-folder 1.11)
  - Plan III Revised, undated 1970 (Box-folder 1.12)
- Committees, undated 1955-1972
  - Central Virginia Educational Television, undated 1963-1972 (Box-folder 1.13)
  - Committee for Youth, undated 1962-1966 (Box-folder 1.14)
  - Richmond Council of Women's Organizations, undated 1965-1968 (Box-folder 1.15)
  - Richmond Federation of Parent-Teacher Associations, undated 1955-1972 (Box-folder 1.16)
  - Summer Job Survey, undated 1956-1969 (Box-folder 1.17)
- Richmond School Board, undated 1958-1980
  - Attrition, undated 1970-1971 (Box-folder 1.18)
  - Brown v. Board 1972 (Box-folder 1.19)
  - Citizens for Excellent Public Schools (CEPS), undated 1970-1972 (Box-folder 1.20)
  - Compulsory Attendance 1963, 1972 (Box-folder 1.21)
  - Correspondence-Miscellaneous, undated 1958, 1964, 1966-1972, 1979 (Box-folder 1.22)
  - Graves Junior High School Evaluation Report 1967 (Box-folder 1.23)
  - Identifying Our Community Problems Survey 1970s (Box-folder 2.1)
  - Kindergarten 1965, 1976 (Box-folder 2.2)
  - Murphy v. Board 1970-1971 (Box-folder 2.3)
  - Northside School Study Committee 1957, 1969 (Box-folder 2.4)
  - Paxman v. Wilkerson 1975 (Box-folder 2.5)
  - Richmond Education Association 1970-1972 (Box-folder 2.6)
  - Richmond School Board, undated 1959, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 2.7)
  - Richmond School Board 1971-1972 (Box-folder 2.8)
  - Rules and Regulations of the School Board 1967 (Box-folder 2.9)
  - Safety 1970-1972 (Box-folder 2.10)
  - School Budgets, undated 1958, 1960, 1964, 1970-1972, 1980 (Box-folder 2.11)
  - Sex Education in the Public Schools, undated 1968-1970, 1973 (Box-folder 2.12)
  - Sidney School Program (for pregnant teens) 1971-1972 (Box-folder 2.13)
  - Speeches, undated 1970 (Box-folder 2.14)
  - Suspension, undated 1971-1972 (Box-folder 2.15)
  - Tax Study Commission, undated 1971-1972 (Box-folder 2.16)
  - Teacher's Salary, undated 1958, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 2.17)
  - Technical Training Center, undated 1968, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 2.18)
  - Willett, Henry I. 1958, 1968 (Box-folder 2.19)
- Richmond School Board Minutes 1961-1972
  - Minute Book 1961-1964 (Box 2)
  - Minute Book 1964-1966 (Box 2)
  - Minute Book 1966-1969 (Box 2)
  - Minute Book 1969-1971 (Box 3)
  - Minute Book 1971-1972 (Box 3)
- Publications, undated 1948-1982
  - Publications, Bulletins, Flyers 1967-1972 (Box-folder 3.1)
  - St. Luke's Hospital 1982 (Box-folder 3.2)
  - Annexation Area Street Name Index and Maps 1970 (Box 3)
  - Annexation Information (Box 3)
  - Annual Report of the Richmond Public Schools 1962-1963 (Box 3)
  - Can We Afford to Close Our Public Schools? (Box 3)
  - A Decade of Decision 1954-1964 (Box 3)
  - Education an Investment in People (Box 3)
  - Education in Richmond (Box 3)
  - Essay on Quality in Public Education (Box 3)
  - Facts About your Schools (Box 3)
  - Federation of Parent-Teacher Associations of Richmond Yearbook 1955-1956 (Box 3)
  - Federation of Parent-Teacher Associations of Richmond Yearbook 1956-1957 (Box 3)
  - Federation of Parent-Teacher Associations of Richmond Yearbook 1960-1961 (Box 3)
  - Financing Virginia's Future (Box 3)
  - Freedom to Teach, Freedom to Learn (Box 3)
  - Governing of School Districts (Box 3)
  - Governing the Virginia Metropolitan Areas: An Assessment (Box 3)
  - Guidelines for Professional Negotiation (Box 3)
  - Handbook for Junior Primary Teachers (Box 3)
  - How Classroom Desegregation Will Work (Box 3)
  - Incentives for Quality Teaching (Box 3)
  - Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court Annual Report 1961 (Box 3)
  - Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court Annual Report 1966 (Box 3)
  - Let's Vacation at Home! (Box 3)
  - New Day for Urban Child (Box 3)
  - Our Children Their Growth in Citizenship (Box 3)
  - Partners in Education (Box 3)
  - Policies of the Virginia School Boards Association (Box 3)
  - Public Interest in How Teachers Organize (Box 3)
  - Report of Advisory Committees for the Consolidation of the City of Richmond and Henrico County (Box 3)
  - Richmond and the James (Box 3)
  - Richmond Public Schools Report of the Survey Commission (Box 3)
  - Richmond's Classroom (Box 3)
  - Roles, Responsibilities, Relationships of the School Board, Superintendent and Staff (Box 3)
  - School Boards Look Ahead (Box 3)
  - Schools at a Glance (Box 3)
  - So You're a Richmond Area Teenager and You're Pregnant (Box 3)
  - Standards of Student Conduct (Box 3)
  - Statistical Report of the Richmond Public Schools 1961-1962 (Box 3)
  - Story of Our City 1782-1965 (Box 3)
  - Swann, et al. v. Charlotte-Mecklenburg Board of Education, et al. (Box 3)
  - This Year with the Parent-Teacher Association of J.E.B. Stuart School 1956-1957 (Box 3)
  - Clippings: Discipline (Box 3)
    NL 11/21/71; TD 2/23/71; TD 3/16/72; NL 6/14/72; NL 4/5/72; NL 3/17/72
  - Clippings: Opening Schools (Box 3)
    NL 4/28/71; NL 2/20/70; NL 2/3/72
  - Clippings: REA (Box 3)
    NL 2/3/71; NL 3/27/71; TD 2/3/71; TD 1/22/71; NL 1/25/71; TD 2/3/71
  - Clippings: Discipline (Box 3)
    NL 3/17/72; NL 3/3/71; NL 9/30/70; NL 9/16/70; NL 12/22/70; NL 12/22/70; NL 9/21/70; TD 3/16/72
  - Clippings: Child Study (Box 3)
    TD 11/26/66; TD 11/14/66; NL 12/29/67; NL 6/3/66; TD 6/3/66; TD 7/15/66; TD 6/3/66; WP 4/23/68; WSJ 3/11/72; NL 12/17/71; NL 1/31/72; TD 2/12/63
  - Clippings: Sex Education (Box 3)
    TD 2/16/68; NL 3/13/70; NL 12/7/69; TD 1/15/66; TD 2/12/53; NL 2/11/63; NL 3/13/70; TD 3/16/70; NL 3/5/70; TD 2/16/71; Lynch News 12/17/69; NL 5/26/71
  - Clippings: Disturbed Youths (Box 3)
    NL 10/25/65; TD 3/15/74; NL 12/10/62; TD 6/7/67; NL 12/6/62; TD 10/9/54; NL 9/17/63; TD 6/7/67; TD 3/4/71; NL 4/14/72; NL 5/17/74
  - Clippings: MCV-RPI Merger (Box 3)
    TD 3/2/68
  - Clippings: Richmond Tech Opens (Box 3)
    TD 3/24/68
  - Clippings: Vocational Center (Box 3)
    TD 5/21/64; NL 3/13/62; NL 8/24/71; NL 4/23/63; TD 4/23/63; NL 4/22/63; NL 4/22/63; NL 4/22/63
  - Clippings: Administration (Box 3)
    TD 2/11/70; TD 4/29/71; TD 4/2/71; NL 3/8/71; TD 3/26/72; TD 3/26/72; TD 5/18/71; TD 4/24/71; TD 5/3/60; NL 7/26/62; NL 5/18/71; NL 4/21/71; TD 6/20/62; NL 4/24/62; TD 4/24/62; TD 5/13/62; NL 9/29/61; TD 7/6/61; TD 3/11/68; NL 9/15/63; TD 1/12/60; NL 4/16/65; NL 7/31/59
  - Clippings: PTA (Box 3)
    NL 2/12/62; TD 2/13/62; NL 3/27/61; NL 3/19/59; TD 2/3/71; NL 4/14/58; TD 11/13/68; NL 4/16/65; NL 2/25/72; NL 3/13/62; NL 5/4/64; TD 1/19/64; TD 4/3/64; TD 4/14/58; TD 3/9/59; NL 12/11/61; NL 3/10/58; NL 2/25/72; NL 3/13/62
  - Clippings: Obscenity Laws (Box 3)
    NL 12/19/59; NL 12/3/59; TD 12/1/59; TD 12/2/59; NL 12/2/59
  - Clippings: Tuition (Box 3)
    NL 2/3/71; NL 5/16/73; NL 3/4/71; NL 9/6/62; TD 4/26/69; TD 2/12/71; TD 12/11/62; NL 4/30/71; NL 4/24/71; AP 5/4/71
  - Clippings: PTA (Box 3)
    NL 10/26/59; TD 11/25/64; TD 11/29/59; TD 10/27/62; TD 11/7/65
  - Clippings: Private School Tuition (Box 3)
    TD 8/26/71; TD 4/5/62; TD 3/9/71; TD 2/16/72; TD 2/10/72; NL 8/6/70; WP 1/12/72; WP 1/17/72; NL 3/6/72; NL 3/11/72; NL 6/2/72; TD 3/1/72; WP 2/11/72; TD 4/10/71; NL 4/10/71; TD 5/30/71; NL 10/19/70
  - Clippings: Censorship (Box 3)
    TD 2/3/59; TD 3/12/60; NL 3/10/60; TD 2/10/60; NL 2/10/60; TD 6/22/71; NL 2/10/60; NL 1/26/60; TD 6/5/60; TD 2/18/68; NL 11/30/59; NL 12/3/59; NL 5/18/59; TD 1/5/60; NL 10/24/59; TD 7/14/71
  - Clippings: Board Control (Box 3)
    NL 3/18/71; TD 7/31/59; TD 10/2/59; NL 9/29/59; TD 12/8/59; NL 12/15/59; NL 2/16/60
  - Clippings: School Prayer Reports (Box 3)
    NL 10/15/62; NL 7/13/62
  - Clippings: Surveys of Area Schools (Box 3)
    TD 9/11/71; TD 4/24/71; NL 7/22/71; NL 5/14/70; TD 5/23/71; TD 5/18/72; TD 3/8/71; NL 5/18/74; NL 4/19/72; NL 6/16/72; TD 5/9/72; TD 11/28/71; NL 3/30/72; NL 10/19/72; NL 9/11/70; TD 4/12/70; NL 9/19/70
  - Clippings: Budget (Box 3)
    NL 5/6/71; TD 6/4/71; NL 5/1/71; TD 4/23/71; TD 9/4/71; TD 5/7/72; NL 3/5/63; NL 5/9/72; NL 5/30/72; NL 5/10/72; TD 11/18/71; NL 8/10/71; TD 2/18/62; NL 2/8/71; NL 2/8/71; NL 4/8/71; TD 4/8/71; TD 2/2/71; TD 4/8/71; TD 3/30/71; TD 1/26/72; NL 2/16/72; TD 3/30/72; TD 12/16/72; NL 5/11/72; WP 8/4/71; WP 8/4/71; NL 9/25/59; TD 4/10/62; TD 2/20/70; NL 2/20/70
  - Clippings: Summer Jobs (Box 3)
    NL 6/30/66; TD 6/29/66; TD 5/21/57; TD 5/21/57; TD 5/7/57; NL 5/7/57; TD 5/14/57; TD 11/12/56; NL 11/12/56; NL 5/14/57; NL 7/7/56; NL 10/18/56; TD 11/13/53; NL 3/18/57
  - Clippings: Ed. TV (Box 3)
    TD 11/6/63; TD 4/30/64; NL 10/5/62; TD 10/15/63; NL 3/20/64; NL 4/30/64; TD 9/15/63; NL 6/3/64; TD 11/18/64; NL 1/7/64; TD 11/17/64; TD 8/21/64; NL 9/7/66; NL 3/4/71; NL 9/8/71; NL 3/29/71; NL 5/23/72; NL 4/29/71; NL 12/26/64; NL 10/1/70; TD 9/25/70; TD 10/19/70; TD 10/7/70; NL 10/29/70; TD 4/15/69
  - Clippings: School Board (Box 3)
    TD 11/3/71; WP 4/14/72; NL 8/16/71; NL 6/13/72; TD 6/7/72; WP 6/17/72; WP 6/9/72; TD 1/12-19/72; NL 1/12/72; NL 6/15/72; TD 6/15/72; NL 3/30/71; NL 9/7/62; TD 3/25/71; TD 4/14/72; NL 6/6/72; WP 2/10/72; TD 4/7/71; TD 4/7/71; TD 1/3/72; TD 12/16/61; TD 5/7/59; TD 4/22/71; NL 6/18/71; TD 5/27/71; TD 1/1/71; NL 1/1/71; TD 12/18/70; TD 9/18/70; TD 9/18/70; NL 11/9/70; NL 11/27/70; TD 11/10/70; NL 11/16/70; NL 11/16/70; NL 11/9/70; NL 9/30/70; TD 9/16/59
  - Clippings: Schools Consolidation/desegregation. (Box 3)
    NL 3/26/71; TD 5/2/71; WP 9/17/72; NL 4/13/72; TD 1/11/72; WP 1/11/72; NL 4/5/72; VP 4/10/72; TD 2/6/72; WP 1/17/72; WP 1/16/72; WP 1/16/72; NL 1/11/72; TD 1/23/72; WP 8/22/71; WP 1/16/72; NL 8/4/71; NL 8/1/61; NL 8/1/61; TD 12/10/61; NL 12/9/61; NL 8/1/61; NL 5/18/61; NL 5/24/61; NL 7/3/70; TD 7/24/70; TD 6/21/70; NL 7/22/90; TD 8/18/70; TD 8/21/70; NL 8/24/70; NL 7/23/70; NL 7/23/70; NL 4/30/69; TD 2/19/60; AP 12/3/70; TD 6/13/61; TD 11/16/61; TD 12/10/61; TD 12/10/61; TD 8/1/61; NL 9/7/61; TD 12/5/70; NL 4/26/69; TD 9/13/70; TD 9/13/70; TD 9/13/70; TD 9/17/70; TD 9/22/70; TD 9/11/70; NL 10/5/70; TD 11/16/70; TD 12/8/70; NL 10/13/70; TD 9/19/78; NL 10/14/70; NL 10/14/70; NL 10/15/70; TD 9/7/70; NL 7/27/62; NL 2/5/70; TD 7/24/70; TD 8/30/70
  - Clippings: General/Merger (Box 3)
    TD 2/27/61 Chesterfield Pop.; NL 6/28/61 Chesterfield Pop.; TD 11/10/58 Cities Future; TD 5/12/61 Jaycees Examine City; NL 6/30/61 Annexation Suits; NL 6/27/61 Annexation Suits; NL 6/22/61 Merger Area; TD 6/24/61 Woodward Views DuPont; NL 12/28/59 Merger; NL 6/27/61 Clearing 17th St.; TD 3/31/60 Redistricting; TD 6/13/60 Redistrict Committee; TD 5/21/61 Redistrict Committee; TD 11/7/61 Merger; TD 6/29/61 Merger; TD 10/21/61 Merger; NL 9/25/61 Merger; TD 10/24/61 Motorcade Scheduled Here Today; TD 4/25/61 Richmond Housing; NL 10/14/61 Voters Plan Talks on Merger; TD 12/1/61 Women Take Merger Appeal; NL 10/20/61 Women Take Merger Appeal; NL 9/23/61 Merger; NL 12/5/63 Discrimination Against Women; NL 11/10/63 Sales Tax Plan Not Expected; TD 11/17/61 Richmond-Henrico Merger Proposal; TD 8/1/61 Plan to Merge City; TD 11/18/61 Caution on Merger; NL 11/6/61 Merger Foes Are Reproved; NL 10/23/61 Nod Given to Merger; NL 8/24/61 What's In It for Him?; TD 12/12/61 If you don't know; TD 12/15/61 Chesterfield, too; TD 12/13/61 City-County Merger Defeated by Henrico; TD 12/13/61 The Real Losers; NL 8/18/61 Five-Borough Merger Set-Up; NL 9/6/61 New Merger Proposal; TD 8/4/61 RCA May Disband If Merger Plan; TD 8/22/61 No Merger Plan Can Be Perfect; NL 8/18/61 Long View; TD 10/10/61 Council, Board Agree on Terms for Merger; NL 11/9/61 Women Believed Key Factor In Area Voting on Merger; TD 11/22/61 Merger Vote to Bring Many Changes in Area; TD 8/27/61 What You Should Know About Merger; NL 8/18/61 Composition of GMC Approving Merger; TD 11/21/61 Area Consolidation Would Accelerate Economic Growth; TD 11/5/61 Here Are Key Points in Merger Debate; TD 12/17/61 Merger Defeat Margin Was Surprise; NL 11/29/61 Why Merge; NL 11/2/61 Joint Agreement for Consolidation; NL 8/1/61 Heading Toward Merger; TD 8/22/61 No Merger Plan Can Be Perfect; NL 10/6/61 Merger; Happy, Merger Mad; NL 8/3/61 Merger and the Courts; NL 8/1/61 Favorable to Merger Plan; TD 11/14/61 Financial Burdens of County to Grow; TD 11/19/61 Eyes of Nation on City-County Merger Voting; NL 3/11/68 Richmond Fared on Assembly; TD 11/14/68 Registration; TD 12/29/61 Voice of the People; TD 11/12/61 City Center of Urban Galaxy; TD 11/18/61 Triple-A Club; TD 12/16/61 Assessment; NL 11/11/68 Willett's Monument; TD 11/18/70 Merhige Add 3 Defendants; TD 11/10/70 Book Preserve Rights; NL 11/1/65 Books for Human Development; TD 9/26/59 Committee Named to Study Salaries of City Teachers; TD 4/15/58 Proposal to Drop Kindergarten Held; TD 8/19/60 Teacher's Pay Plan; NL 6/16/71 Old School Said Hampering New Methods; TD 8/10/75 St. Luke's Hospital; TD 10/17/82 St. Luke's Hospital; TD 10/7/70 Largely Black Schools Berated
  - Clippings: Voters (Box 3)
    NL 4/12/61; NL 3/28/60; TD 10/13/63; TD 11/5/70
  - Clippings: Annexation (Box 3)
    TD 5/5/61; NL 7/6/61; TD 11/16/61; NL 12/13/61; NL 12/19/61; TD 12/19/61; NL 12/19/61
  - Clippings: Merger (Box 3)
    TD 12/10/61; NL 7/25/61; NL 12/23/61; TD 12/10/61; NL 11/24/61; TD 11/14/61; NL 9/17/70; TD 11/9/70; NL 12/14/70; TD 7/24/70; TD 11/17/70